Okay טוב, Tov, today's דף Daf officially is ע"ט, Ayin-Tet, 79. We're
a little behind, we started at the very bottom of ע"ח עמוד
א'. Ayin-Chet Amud Aleph. We are dealing with the issue of the
women who are forbidden to a כהן. Kohein. Very important discussions yesterday,
first of all distinguishing between the definition of a חללה Chalalah and
a זונה. Zonah. Also the very critical question about whether it's a
prohibition of marriage or of sex. The גמרא Gemara discusses the כהן
גדול Kohein Gadol and makes it clear that it's a prohibition for
well, marriage followed by sex is the איסור issur of לא יקח.
Lo Yikach. According to אביי Abaye just marriage alone is that איסור,
issur, is that prohibition. And sex alone is the איסור issur of
לא יחלל. Lo Yechalel. By מחזיר גרושתו Machzir Grushaso not relating to
כהן, Kohein, it's marriage that culminates in sex. The one very important
question that the גמרא Gemara never directly discusses is what about a
normal כהן? Kohein? And there ראב"ד Ravad and רש"י Rashi think that
that's just like the כהן גדול, Kohein Gadol, that there's an איסור
issur of sex by itself. According to רמב"ם Rambam by a normal
כהן Kohein the איסור issur is just marriage, there is no איסור
issur of sex, there's just an איסור issur of marriage, which is
very significant
because one of the issues we've been discussing is nowadays when you
deal with those issues about a כהן Kohein and a גרושה Grusha
or כהן Kohein and a גיורת Giyores and how when they fall
in love and then there's a question about getting married. Sometimes it's
by trying to find a way to say that the woman wasn't
really a גרושה, Grusha, or maybe she was one of the גיורת,
Giyores, maybe you can find out that she really is descendant of
Jews, or to say that the כהן Kohein isn't really a כהן.
Kohein. Sometimes those solutions are not available and then according to those
positions, the position of the רמב"ם Rambam is they don't actually have
a halachic קידושין, kiddushin, they wouldn't actually be in violation, although the
children would still be חללים. Chalalim. Because the other thing that we
learned yesterday is when a כהן Kohein has sex with a woman
who is forbidden to him as a כהן, Kohein, then the woman
becomes a חללה Chalalah and the children become חללים, Chalalim, and that
does apply even to a כהן הדיוט, Kohein Hedyot, so that would
be an interesting sort of not full solution, but anyway that's interesting
at least to note that even though the children are חללים, Chalalim,
for the רמב"ם Rambam there's no prohibition without marriage. That's in terms
of the general prohibition. And then we turned our focus to the
issue of גיורת, Giyores,
where nowhere in the תורה Torah says that a גיורת Giyores is
forbidden.
We saw according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it's actually some type
of a stigma status, some type of thing that somebody starts as
a non-Jew and therefore they can even pass down, even the child
of a male גר Ger according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
be פסול possul to a כהן. Kohein. According to another position in
the גמרא, Gemara, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, if
one parent is exactly born Jew it's not a problem, but if
both parents are גרים, Geirim, that also the status that passes it
down. And finally the position of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that says
it's only a problem if the person actually converted herself. A child
of גרים Geirim is not a problem. And a fourth position, that
of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, that said that
it's actually only if the person converts when she's the age of
three or older, under than that it is not a problem. We
are going to see that we rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi,
that even if the person converts under the age of three they
are פסול possul to a כהן. Kohein. And there's an interesting question,
let's say they actually were conceived as a non-Jew and converted in
utero, which happens when a pregnant woman converts. And according to that,
according to many ראשונים Rishonim because of the language of the גמרא
Gemara that says she has to be נזרעה בישראל, Nizre'ah b'Yisrael, seeds—the
seed is planted as meaning conceived as a Jew, that even that
woman would be forbidden to a כהן. Kohein. So according to all
of those, it has nothing to do with any concern of sexual
activity on behalf of the woman, it just has to do with
the fact that somehow she began life as a non-Jew.
And that is what?
Almost sounds like מה לזו בביאה? mah la-zu b'bi'ah?
Well what can I tell you, it's true though, because where's the
פסוק? pasuk? As a point—as opposed to רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai, who's the—by distinguishing between the age of three and
under three and over three based on the פסוק pasuk by מדין,
Midian, אשר לא ידעו משכב זכר, asher lo yadu mishkav zachar, seems
to have something to do with either having had sex or the
possibility of having had sex. Now where is this learned from? So
we learned yesterday that the גמרא Gemara learns it out from the
פסוק pasuk by יחזקאל Yechezkel that says that
they can only marry בתולות מזרע בית ישראל. Besulos mi-Zera Beis Yisrael.
So from the Jewish seed, from Jewish descent.
So according to a number of ראשונים Rishonim that is a דרבנן
d'rabbanan or דברי סופרים, divrei sofrim, it is not a דאורייתא. d'oraisa.
According to others we learn from that פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel
what the תורה's Torah definition of זונה Zonah is. Funny to put
her in a זונה Zonah category, again that seems again to connect
to the idea of sex. The נפקא מינה nafka mina whether it's
דאורייתא d'oraisa or דרבנן, d'rabbanan, one נפקא מינה nafka mina is whether
the children would be חללים. Chalalim. If it's not really a דאורייתא
d'oraisa prohibition, then we have never seen this idea that there's a
rabbinic category of חלל, Chalal, although it's an interesting question also what's
the story about a child of a חלוצה chalutzah actually, maybe there
is a rabbinic category of חלל, Chalal, but anyway, according to a
number of פוסקים Poskim if this is only rabbinic, the children would
not be חללים Chalalim between a כהן Kohein and a גיורת. Giyores.
So that's interesting. The other interesting part is though the flip way.
That way if you have it as a דרבנן, Derabbanan, it is
less severe. But the other part though is if you have it
as a דרבנן, Derabbanan, then it's more this totally this פסוק Pasuk
in יחזקאל Yechezkel and it's absolute, if they're not of Jewish descent,
end of story. Whereas if you focus on that as telling you
the problem of the תורה's Torah category of זונה, Zona, it's explaining
to you what's in the category of זונה, Zona, then that ultimately
seems to link to a concept of sex. So for example, there's
a רש״י Rashi in יבמות Yevamot that seems to go against everything
we're saying here, that seems to indicate that a גיורת Giyoret is
only a problem if she actually had sex as a non-Jewish woman.
Completely against everything we're saying here. But at least it shows you
that if you're fitting it into the זונה Zona category, it might
somehow be linked to a concept of sex. So there are some
פוסקים Poskim nowadays that I know, nobody, I don't think anybody's written
about this, but are like speculating about scenarios where let's say somebody
is raised Jewish, I mean essentially it would be not different than
the גמרא's Gemara case about a woman that converted while the while
the child was in utero, or let's say a child is adopted
as a very young child and raised in a Jewish family. So
even though she started not Jewish, there's no, you know, I mean
the whole idea that being raised as a non-Jew means you're more
likely to have had sex at a, you know, pre-marital sex or
whatever, I mean we can even question those realities nowadays, although we
do live in a generally sexually promiscuous or permissive world, but still.
But let's say raised in a פרום Frum Jewish family and so
on and converted, you know, at a young age, would you put
that in the same זונה Zona category? Okay, but, you know, that
is something to speculate on, but in our גמרא, Gemara, there is
nothing that hints to the idea that it is about a concern
that she actually had sex. All of these rules are learned from
this פסוק Pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, and the very fact that it's
based on the idea of even if she was conceived, even if
she converted was conceived in utero, she still is in that category,
does not seem to allow for that for that type of an
approach. But there are other גמרות Gemarot and those ראשונים Rishonim who
want to say that this ultimately becomes a זונה Zona problem, a
דאורייתא Deoraita problem, on the one hand it's more weighty because it's
דאורייתא, Deoraita, but on the other hand it somewhat links it to
a world of having had sex, and that maybe can allow for
some exploring of exactly what those parameters are. Alright, so that's a
recap of yesterday.
Let's now continue. Last line on ע״ח עמוד א׳. Ayin Chet Amud
Alef. אמר ליה רב נחמן לרבא. Amar Leh Rav Nachman LeRava. So
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to רבא. Rava. Okay, now top of
ע״ח עמוד ב׳. Ayin Chet Amud Bet. האי קרא, Hai Kra, this
פסוק Pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, רישא בכהן גדול וסיפא בכהן הדיוט. Reisha
BeKohen Gadol VeSeifa BeKohen Hedyot. So what do you do with this
פסוק? Pasuk? The beginning of the פסוק Pasuk says you can't marry
an אלמנה, Almana, which is talking about a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
and the end says כי אם בתולות מזרע בית ישראל, Ki Im
Betulot MiZera Beit Yisrael, which is what which we say refers to
a normal כהן Kohen that he has to marry and that's where
we learn out the prohibition of a convert.
כי אם בתולות מזרע בית ישראל Ki Im Betulot MiZera Beit Yisrael
refers to a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, wouldn't it?
No, we said it refers to a normal כהן. Kohen. It should.
You know, that's the way we're choosing to read it. So what
how do you split this פסוק? Pasuk? The beginning is a כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, can't marry an אלמנה, Almana, and the end is
a normal כהן Kohen where you learn that it has to be
somebody born Jewish. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה אין, Amar
Leh In, yes. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכתב קרא הכי, VeKetav
Kra Hachi, can a פסוק Pasuk be written that way? Half about
one group of group of people and the other about another half?
אמר ליה אין, Amar Leh In, yes, דכתיב, DeKetiv, ונר אלקים טרם
יכבה, VeNer Elokim Terem Yichbe, this is by שמואל, Shmuel, who, you
know, is given over to עלי הכהן, Eli HaKohen, and the light
of God had not yet been extinguished, ושמואל שכב בהיכל ה׳, VeShmuel
Shochev BeHeichal Hashem, and שמואל Shmuel was lying down in the sanctuary.
So how could שמואל Shmuel be lying down in the sanctuary? For
lo, אין ישיבה בעזרה אלא למלכי בית דוד בלבד, Ein Yeshiva BeAzara
Ella LeMalchei Beit David Bilvad, nobody's allowed to sit, even sit, in
the עזרה, Azara, in the courtyard, except for kings of from the
house of David. אלא, Ella, here's how to read the פסוק: Pasuk:
ונר אלקים טרם יכבה בהיכל ה׳, VeNer Elokim Terem Yichbe BeHeichal Hashem,
the light had not yet had not extinguished in the sanctuary, the
light of the מנורה, Menorah, that's how we're reading it, although you
could have read that פסוק Pasuk a little more
metaphorically, ושמואל שכב במקומו, VeShmuel Shochev BiMkumo, and שמואל Shmuel was lying
down where he was lying down, not in the עזרה. Azara. He
was lying in the, you know, in the outer precincts of the
temple. So you take the היכל ה׳ Heichal Hashem at the end
of the פסוק Pasuk and you take it out of its context
and you put it at the beginning of the פסוק. Pasuk. So
sometimes you're able to do that. To chop up a פסוק. Pasuk.
Not exactly the same point. It's not the same thing.
I know, but where it's the same thing is that the
end of the פסוק Pasuk was talking about a regular כהן. Kohen.
We're going to get there. Alright, we're going to get there. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, והאלמנה אשר תהיה
אלמנה מכהן יקחו, VeHaAlmana Asher Tihye Almana MiKohen Yikchu, some an אלמנה
Almana who is a widow from a כהן Kohen they can marry.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מכהן אין מישראל לא? MiKohen
In MiYisrael Lo? You can marry a widow of a כהן, Kohen,
you can't marry a widow of a ישראל? Yisrael? If this if
the end of the פסוק Pasuk is already talking that says מזרע
בית ישראל, MiZera Beit Yisrael, it's talking about a כהן הדיוט, Kohen
Hedyot, so a כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot can marry a normal אלמנה.
Almana. הכי קאמר, Hachi Ka'amar, no, this is how you have to
read it.
מכהן יקחו משאר כהנים יקחו. MiKohen Yikchu MiShe'ar Kohanim Yikchu. That all
the other כהנים Kohanim can marry an אלמנה. Almana. Meaning the way
they're reading the פסוק Pasuk is: אלמנה וגרושה לא יקחו, Almana VeGerusha
Lo Yikchu, don't marry an אלמנה Almana and a גרושה, Gerusha, that's
a כהן Kohen that's a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. כי אם זרע
מבית ישראל Yisrael *ki im zera mibeit yisrael* כי אם בתולות מזרע
בית ישראל *ki im betulot mizera beit yisrael* is the כהן Kohen,
הדיוט *kohen hedyot* which we say means a naturally born Jew, not
a
גיורת *giyoret*, but somebody who is an אלמנה *almanah*, מכהן יקחו *mikohane
yikchu*, all the other כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim* they who are כהן Kohen
הדיוט *kohen hedyot*, they can marry an אלמנה *almanah*.
And מכהן יקחו *mikohane yikchu* all the...
משאר כהנים Kohanim *mishar kohanim*, all the other כהנים *kohanim*, not the
כהן Kohen. גדול *kohen gadol* we were talking about at the beginning
of the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*, but the other כהנים *kohanim*, they can
marry an אלמנה *almanah*. Okay, look this is why they wanted to
be גונז ספר יחזקאל *gonez sefer yechezkel* because the פשט *pshat* of
the פסוקים *psukim* contradict the תורה *Torah* and we're reading it in
a way to rectify it. Not just in this. תניא נמי הכי
*Tanya nami hachi*. We taught similarly. מכהן יקחו *mikohane yikchu*, משאר כהנים
יקחו *mishar kohanim yikchu*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר *Rabbi Yehudah omer*
no, מן המשיאים לכהונה יקחו *min hamasi'im likhunah yikchu*. What it means
is that you can marry a widow, a person who is a
widow from people from men who could marry off their daughters to
כהנים *kohanim*. Which man cannot marry his daughter to a כהן Kohen.
*kohen*? A גר *ger*. This is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehudah*
who says a גר *ger*, a daughter of a גר *ger* can't
marry a כהן Kohen, *kohen*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda לטעמיה דאמר בת
גר זכר כבת חלל challal, זכר *Rabbi Yehudah leta'ameh d'amar bat ger
zachar kebat chalal zachar*. So therefore a גר *ger*, his daughter can't
marry a כהן kohen. *kohen*, right? That's רבי יהודה'ס *Rabbi Yehudah's* position.
And therefore his אלמנה *almanah* can't marry a כהן *kohen*. Why can't
a גר'ס *ger's* אלמנה *almanah* marry a כהן *kohen*? Because if his
daughter becomes is פסולה *psulah*, his wife is also פסולה *psulah*. Essentially
he makes his wife into a type of a חללה *chalalah*. Okay,
כל שאתה נושא בתו אתה נושא אלמנתו *kol she'atah nosei bito atah
nosei almanato*. If you can marry his daughter, you can marry his
widow. וכל שאי אתה נושא בתו אי אתה נושא אלמנתו *vechol she'ei
atah nosei bito ei atah nosei almanato*. You cannot marry his daughter,
you cannot marry his widow. So that's how we reconcile the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* in יחזקאל *Yechezkel*, but bottom line is
from this פסוק Passuk? *pasuk* in יחזקאל *Yechezkel*, which clearly goes against
פשט *pshat* of the תורה *Torah*, we learn out the idea that
the איסור *issur* of a גיורת *giyoret*, of a כהן *kohen* to
marry a גיורת *giyoret*. And then these different opinions, is it such
a problem that it passes down from father to child? Or is
it only a problem in somebody who actually converted herself? Or according
to רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon Bar Yochai*, the most lenient
position, only if she converted after the age of three. Now how
do we rule? So here we come here here's the conclusion of
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. רבי יוסי אומר אף גר שנשא גיורת *Rabbi
Yose omer af ger shenasa giyoret*. So רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* says
the child of a גר וגיורת *ger u'giyoret* is fine. It's only
a problem about the person who converted herself. אמר amar רב Rav
המנונא משמיה דעולא הלכה halacha, כרבי יוסי *Amar Rav Hamnuna mishmeih d'Ulla
halacha ke'Rabbi Yose*. We rule like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. Okay, that's
a big deal. At least a person who is a child of
converts can marry a כהן *kohen*. וכן אמר amar רבה בר בר
חנה הלכה כרבי יוסי *Vechane amar Rabbah bar bar Chana halacha ke'Rabbi
Yose*. We rule like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*. But that being said,
ומיום שחרב בית המקדש נהגו כהנים סלסול בעצמן כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב
*Umi-yom shecharav Beit Hamikdash nahagu kohanim silsul be'atzman ke'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov*.
Once the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* was destroyed, the כהנים *kohanim* adopted
like Michael saying, מעלה ביוחסין *ma'alah beyuchsin*, a higher level amongst themselves
and they ruled in practice, they didn't rule like but they practiced
like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov*. רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* is the one who says that it's
the which one was he? He was the one that said ישראל
שנשא גיורת בתו כשרה לכהונה וגר שנשא *Yisrael shenasa giyoret bito kesherah
likhunah veger shenasa*, right, only the daughter of two converts they would
not marry. The daughter of two converts would be a problem. It's
actually interesting that they began this higher level of practice after the
בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* was destroyed. You would have thought when there
was a בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* and they were serving in the
בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* they would have adopted this higher level, maybe
it's a way to react against it like, don't think that we've
lost our קדושה *kedushah*, you know, we lost our status now that
there's no בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. No, we're actually going to adopt
even greater stringency. So they would actually not marry the daughter of
two גירים *gerim*. אמר רב Rav נחמן אמר לי הונא באו לימלך
מורים לו כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב *Amar Rav Nachman amar li Huna
ba'u limaleich morim lo ke'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov*. If somebody asks a
שאלה *she'elah*, you פסק'ן pasken *pasken* to them like רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov*. You shouldn't marry the daughter of two
גירים *gerim*. נשא *nasa* once the person gets married, אין מוציאין אותה
ממנו כרבי יוסי *ein motzi'in otah mimenu ke'Rabbi Yose*. Then בדיעבד *bedi'avad*
you rule like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* that the daughter of גירים
*gerim* is even of two גירים *gerim* can marry a כהן *kohen*
if there's only somebody who converted herself. Yes, Charlie.
Are there any other cases where the הלכה *halacha* is not like
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* in the משנה Mishnah.
*Mishnah*?
I'm sure there are but I cannot tell you offhand. Okay. All
right, next משנה mishna *Mishnah*. So that is the end of כהן
*kohen* and a גיורת *giyoret*, very very relevant cases nowadays, some of
the more challenging cases in הלכה *halacha* are dealing with those situations.
Okay, next משנה mishna *Mishnah*. האומר בני זה ממזר mamzer, *Ha'omer beni
zeh mamzer*. Now we are getting out of the יוחסין yuchsin, *yuchsin*
in terms of identifying who is who
and determining what are the parameters, you know, the child of whom
can marry whom, the child of a חלל challal, *chalal*, the child
of a גר *ger*, and now we're getting with the issue of
who is believed to make claims about somebody's הלכתי *halachic* status. So
if a man says my son this son of mine is a
ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*, אינו נאמן *eino ne'eman* he's not believed. פליגא *paliga*?
Partly אין אדם משים
עצמו רשע *ein adam meisim atzmo rasha*? Partly אין אדם משים עצמו
רשע *ein adam meisim atzmo rasha*, partly also because presumably you know
who the mother is. So if you know the mother is and
you know the mother isn't related to him, then the only way
he's saying that it's a ממזר mamzer. *mamzer* is basically saying he's
not my son. So he's actually testifying about somebody that isn't his
son. A person might be believed about his son, but here he's
actually testifying, everybody gets the point? If you know the mother is,
and the mother's his wife, and you know that his wife isn't
his sister or something like
that. Well if
somebody else is the father, why do you have more belief than
believability than anybody else, any other random person off the street? Okay,
but if he's saying that this person that you've all assumed was
my kosher wife is actually my sister, right, then it's also an
issue about משים עצמו רשע, you know, and other types of issues.
He really can't just literally say, "Yeah, you know what?
I was away this whole year on a business trip." Yes, that's
a different story. But that's not him being believed, okay?
Circumstantial evidence. Okay, ואפילו שניהם מודים. ve'afilu sheneihem modim. Even if the
mother agrees, "Yes, this child is a ממזר, mamzer there's another man
is the father of my child." Even then, you wouldn't believe that.
That's a חידוש, chiddush, right? Now, ואפילו שניהם על עובר, ve'afilu sheneihem
al ubar, even if the child is in utero, שבמעיה. she'be'me'eha. ממזר
הוא, mamzer hu, if
he said, if they said he's a ממזר, mamzer אינם נאמנים, einam
ne'emanim, they're not believed. רבי יהודה אומר נאמנים, Rabbi Yehuda omer ne'emanim,
no they are believed. And we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara it
sounds like, and the גמרא's Gemara going to say even the first
case. Let's take a look. מאי ואפילו שניהם? mai ve'afilu sheneihem? What's
the חידוש chiddush if both of them agree when the child is
in utero? It's a big
חידוש. chiddush. לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka'amar. לא מיבעיא איהו lo
mibaya ihu דלא קים ליה. delo kim leh. It goes without saying
if he's not believed, how does he know who the father is?
Okay? I mean, how does he know enough to say he's not
the father? I mean, obviously you could make up circumstances where he
would know. But anyway, אלא אפילו איהי דקים לה, ela afilu ihi
dekim lah, even she, who she knows who the father is, לא
מהימנא, lo mehemana, she's not believed. And why? Why should she be
believed? Where do you get that עד אחד ed echad is believed?
This is a question about personal status, and you would need for
personal status, אין דבר שבערווה פחות משניים, ein davar shebe'ervah pachot mishnayim,
you would need two witnesses. So even the people that are in
a position to know, they're not believed, they're just an עד אחד.
ed echad. And anyway, she's a woman. Okay? But anyway, but it
doesn't matter like, nobody here is believed. ולא מיבעיא היכא דאית ליה
חזקה דכשרות, velo mibaya heicha de'it leh chazakah de'kashrut, not only in
a case where the child's already been born and
we've been presuming that the child is okay and he has a
presumption of being כשר, kasher, דלא מהימן, delo meheiman, אלא אפילו עובר
נמי, ela afilu ubar nami, even in utero, דליכא חזקה דכשרות, delika
chazakah de'kashrut, nobody has any presumption yet about his status, he's doesn't
yet, he's not yet a person to have an identity, a halachic
status, לא מהימני, lo meheimni, they're not believed. Okay? So this is
a basic principle, עד אחד ed echad is not believed, unless you're
in a position, not, it's not enough to be in a position
to know, you have to have a special status of being given
more believability than a normal person. And that's going to be רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda, position. So let's take a look. רבי יהודה אומר
נאמנים, Rabbi Yehuda omer ne'emanim, one minute, they're believed. כדתניא, kidetanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: Beraita: יכיר. yakir. It says, כי את הבכור
בן השנואה יכיר לתת לו פי שנים. ki et habechor ben hasnuah
yakir latet lo pi shenayim. The father should recognize his firstborn son
to give him the double portion. Okay, יכירנו לאחרים. yakirenu leachairim. It
means that he identifies him to others, even if others don't know
who the firstborn is, he's believed to identify who his firstborn son
is. מכאן אמר רבי יהודה, mikan amar Rabbi Yehuda, נאמן אדם לומר
זה בני בכור. ne'eman adam lomar zeh beni bechor. He's believed to
say, "This is my firstborn son." Fine, everybody agrees to that. But
now רבי יהודה takes it one step further. וכשם שנאמן אדם לומר
זה בני בכור, כך נאמן אדם לומר זה בן גרושה וזה בן
חלוצה. u'keshem she'ne'eman adam lomar zeh beni bechor, kach ne'eman adam lomar
zeh ben gerushah v'zeh ben chalutzah. He's believed to say that the
mother is a גרושה gerushah or חלוצה, chalutzah, I'm a כהן, the
child is a חלל, and presumably, if he's believed to say the
child is a חלל, he's also believed to say the child is
a ממזר. Of course, again, saying the child is a ממזר goes
one step further. If he says the mother's my sister, maybe that's
similar to saying the mother's a גרושה. gerushah. But if he's saying
that this is another man's child, then he's not even testifying about
his own child. So that's a much bigger חידוש. chiddush. Anyway, but
that's what רבי יהודה learns that once a person is believed to
recognize his child as a בכור, bechor, he's recognized to make any
claim about the status of his child. All right?
וחכמים אומרים אינו נאמן. vachachamim omrim eino ne'eman. He's not believed in
anything other than בכור. bechor. אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא,
amar leh Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak le'Rava, בשלמא לרבי יהודה היינו דכתיב
יכיר. bishlama le'Rabbi Yehuda hainu de'chtiv yakir. רבי יהודה, that's a חידוש,
chiddush, that you're believed to identify the status of your child, the
man is at least, not the woman, not the mother, which is
again ironic. אלא לרבנן יכיר למה לי? ela le'rabbanan yakir lamah li?
What's the חידוש chiddush to say that you identify who your בכור
bechor is? בצריך הכרה. betzarich hakarah. Yes, in a case where it's
not known to people who the firstborn is, you come into a
new town, nobody knows who your firstborn is. Or you had two
wives and you had twins, right? Exactly, you could have cases where
you need testimony who the firstborn is. בצריך הכרה. betzarich hakarah. למאי
הלכתא? lemai hilchata? לתת לו פי שנים. latet lo pi shenayim. For
בכור bechor purposes. So the גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא למה לי קרא?
pishita lamah li kra? Of course you could be believed, why do
you need a פסוק? Passuk מיגו דאי בעי יהיב ליה מתנה. migo
de'i ba'ei yahiv leh matanah. Since I could, if I wanted to
lie, I could have just given this guy a double portion by
just giving him a gift. מי לא יהיב ליה? mi lo yahiv
leh? So I could have given him. So then I should be
believed to say he's a בכור bechor and he gets a double
portion because I, you know, I don't need the פסוק Passuk to
tell me that, I could have done it if I wanted to
anyway because I could have just given him a gift. Of course,
the funny thing is, if you want to give him a gift,
another child would have had a double portion. If you wanted to
give everybody else an equal portion and him a double, you'd have
to distribute all your money as a gift and have none of
it as inheritance, which also in theory could work. Of course, the,
you know, but then you'd have to worry about the taxes.
I mean, nowadays it'd be a big difference about whether somebody gets
it as an inheritance or as a gift in terms of taxes.
But okay, the גמרא Gemara wasn't dealing with that. So the גמרא
Gemara says, of course you're believed, you could have just done it
as a gift. So why would you not be believed? So the
גמרא Gemara says, so no... No no no you wouldn't be believed
it wouldn't work for property that you inherited after you gave the
gift. So when you say this is my firstborn son, that statement
is going to work on any earnings and money that you get
after you make that statement, and then you'll live another twenty years
and then you'll die, and everything you've earned in that last twenty
years also he gets a double portion. Whereas if you wanted to
give it as a gift, it would only work on what you
already own. It wouldn't work on your stuff. Right, but but this
is telling you that you're believed to be יכיר Yakir twenty years
before you die. Okay, that I wouldn't have known that you would
be believed twenty years before you die in a statement to be
effective for everything else that you've earned afterwards. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, but according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir דאמר אדם
מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם d’amar adam makne davar she’lo ba l’olam
יכיר למה לי? Yakir lama li? But according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir you can give a gift for things you don't yet own.
So why did I need the פסוק? Passuk Even without the פסוק
of יכיר, Yakir, I could have given this kid, I could say
I'm giving you a double portion as a gift on everything I
have now and everything I'll get in the future, and since you
would have that would have worked as a gift, you should be
believed to just say that he's your son. So why do you
need a פסוק to say I mean that he's your firstborn? Why
do you need a פסוק to tell you
that you're believed? So the גמרא Gemara says שנפלו כשהוא גוסס. she’naflu
k’shehu goses. No, because that you're recognizing him as your בכור Bechor
even on property that you inherit when you're on your deathbed. And
that a gift ahead of time wouldn't have worked for. Now why
not? Why can't I give a gift now if I can give
a gift you know מתנת דבר שלא בא לעולם, matnat davar she’lo
ba l’olam, why can't I give a gift now to take effect
on all of the property I have when I'm there at my
deathbed, you know my last minute of my last minute? So רש"י
Rashi makes it sound, he has a very interesting debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. רש"י Rashi makes it sound like when somebody
is literally in their death throes, even though technically they're still alive,
somehow they have lost a certain power of agency and they're not
able to legally you
know do any no no no that's a שכיב מרע. Shichiv mera.
שכיב מרע Shichiv mera is on the deathbed. גוסס Goses is like
literally at the last minutes of life in the throes of death.
Okay, so they've lost agency and they're not able now. If somebody
were to kill this person, it would still be murder. We're not
going ahead and saying like you know euthanasia or anything like that.
They're still considered living, but they're in an interesting category. They're almost
like somewhat like the flip of like a קטן. Katan. You know
like a קטן Katan is also a human being but he doesn't
have legal standing. So to some degree that's how רש"י Rashi would
understand somebody as a גוסס. Goses. תוספות Tosafot strongly disagrees based on
certain גמרות Gemarot and תוספות Tosafot says no no no the only
thing we're dealing with is that often when somebody's a גוסס Goses
they're no longer able to speak. So therefore now it's funny even
if you'd be מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם makne davar she’lo ba
l’olam says תוספות, Tosafot, it would only work when it takes effect
when you're in a position to do it yourself, which includes just
being physically able to do it yourself. So according to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, if you gave a gift to take effect a year
from now and a year from now you were not able not
only to not speak but to not signal to not in any
physical way effect the transaction even though you were a legal entity
empowered to effect the transaction, it would not take effect if you
were not physically able to do so now now. So that is
you know now. So that's an interesting point because you would think
that that shouldn't be a problem of מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם
makne davar she’lo ba l’olam since legally you have that power even
if physically you don't. But that becomes an interesting debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot whether a גוסס Goses somehow does not have
full legal power. רש"י Rashi says he does not. תוספות Tosafot says
he does, he just might not have full physical power to do
it. Okay, yes Michael.
Then two questions, one. Don't we have all these scenarios, a person
said I'm going to give this gift to take effect a minute
before I die? A minute before I die might be a גוסס.
Goses. Is he saying all those wouldn't work?
Yeah, so that's partly what תוספות Tosafot deals with. But it's again,
it's a little different with a מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם makne
davar she’lo ba l’olam might require greater than to do the do
it now to take effect later. I actually slightly misphrased it before.
It wasn't just take effect later, it was actually it was property
that I don't even own now to transfer property that I have
later. So you're right, now I could do an act to take
effect even when I'm a גוסס. Goses. Okay, but what I can't
do is I can't be מקנה makne property that I'll only take
possession of when I'm a גוסס. Goses. You're right, I was a
little imprecise.
And my other question was, you know the גמרא Gemara apparently didn't
address any of this but you know what about my whole case
of the אומדנא? umdena? What?
The אומדנא. umdena.
Like you know again like she knows we know this guy's been
away for...
Yeah but that doesn't matter. That doesn't give you... Oh if we
know he's been away, that's different. Then that's not believing your claim,
that's us just observing the evidence.
But then if he's just... we don't know but like we know
he's not away and we know this guy isn't the father, so
would we then maybe...
Well then it doesn't matter who the father is, ממזר if we
know for sure it's not the father. Right, but if we don't
know then or like she was you know נידה...
niddah... Yeah but that has nothing to do with their claims. Okay,
let's look at the next משנה. Mishna, מי שנתן רשות לשלוחו לקדש
את בתו. Mi she’natan reshus lishlucho lekadesh et bito. Somebody goes gave
a permission to an agent to marry off his daughter, and then
he was concerned that the guy wasn't going to find
someone, והלך וקידש. ve’halach ve’kidesh. and then the father went and married
her himself. Oof, so now we're totally out of the world of
יוחסין, yuchsin we're back to some normal קידושין kiddushin acts here. Right,
very normal. But anyway, to me it's like much less of a
headache than the יוחסין thing. אם שלא קדמו, Im shelo kidmu, קידושיו
קידושין. kidushav kiddushin. If he did the act first,
that was a negating
of the שליחות, shlichus, and the קידושין kiddushin is binding. His קידושין
kiddushin is binding, not the שליח. shaliach. ואם של שלוחו קדמו, Ve'im
shel shlucho kidmu,
if the שליח shaliach did it first, so the שליחות shlichus was
still good, and קידושיו קידושין, kidushav kiddushin, the שליח's shaliach קידושין kiddushin
is good and his act is no good. ואם
אינו ידוע, Ve'im eino yadua, if you don't know who went first,
שניהם נותנים גט, shneihem notnim get, haha very funny, שניהם נותנים גט,
shneihem notnim get, then they both have to... they both have to
give... okay now I have to tell the joke, which is, so
right because they're figuring out they forgot like which is the real...
which is the real חתן, chosson, right? So the story is that
a neighboring town sent to this neighboring town like there was two
single young... young women, two young boys, they sent over two boys
to marry the two women of the neighboring town and they came
but on the way one of them, you know, had an accident
or whatever died and only one boy showed up.
So the... so the parents were arguing like who was, you know,
which girl was going to get the boy, you know? So one
mother said he's for my daughter, the other one said no he's
for my daughter. So they brought it to the rabbi. So the
rabbi said, alright, I got a great solution. יחלקו, yachloku,
right? שלמה Shlomo solution, we'll just cut him in half. Each of
you gets half of him. So one of them says, oh no,
חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, such a נאה na'eh ערליך ehrlich young boy,
how could you do such a thing? It's terrible, חס ושלום, chas
v'shalom, חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, you know, let her... let her have
it. The other one says, no, sounds to me like a good
solution. So he says, oh, you're the real mother-in-law. Alright, anyway. Alright,
moving
on.
So you don't know who the חתן chosson is, anyway we're not
gonna do יחלקו, yachloku, psych Michael for that. So you don't know
who the חתן chosson is. So שניהם נותנים גט. shneihem notnim get.
So if this girl wants to marry some other man, they both
have to give a גט get because either one might be the
חתן. chosson. ואם רצו, Ve'im ratzu, but if they agree, אחד נותן
גט echad noten get ואחד כונס, ve'echad kones, one can agree to...
one will give a גט get and the other can marry because
either the husband gave the גט get and now this is a
new wedding or some guy who wasn't the husband gave a גט
get and this is the guy she was married to anyway that
she's marrying. וכן האשה שנתנה רשות לשלוחה V'chein ha'isha she-natna reshus lishlucha
or a woman gave permission empowered a שליח shaliach לקדשה lekadsha to
marry her, to, you know, accept קידושין kiddushin for her, והלכה וקדשה
עצמה, v'halcha ve-kidsha atzma, then she got anxious and she went and
she married herself off. אם שלה קדמו, Im shela kidmu, if she
married herself before the שליח shaliach did, קידושיה קידושין, kidusheha kiddushin, hers
is binding and implicitly like, you know, she negated the שליח shaliach
or it doesn't really matter because it's moot, she married herself off
so then once the שליח shaliach got around to do it it
didn't mean anything. ואם של שלוחה קדמו, Ve'im shel shlucha kidmu, and
if the שליח shaliach went first, קידושיו קידושין, kidushav kiddushin, the שליח's
shaliach act is still good and obviously her act is too late.
Part of the חידוש chiddush here is you would say that if
she's going around trying to marry herself off even before she has
succeeded maybe that is an implicit negating of the שליח. shaliach. She
sent her שליח shaliach and then she's going and she's like, you
know, it's like trying to find for herself somebody to marry her,
maybe that shows she no longer... No, we say no, she wants
the שליח shaliach to work and... but she, you know, until she
does her own קידושין, kiddushin, she has not negated the שליח. shaliach.
ואם אינם ידועים, Ve'im einam yeduyim, if it's not known, שניהם נותנים
לה גט, shneihem notnim la get, both have to give her a
גט, get, ואם רצו, ve'im ratzu, and if they want, אחד נותן
לה גט echad noten la get ואחד כונס, ve'echad kones, one gives
the גט get and the other marries her. Yes, Michael?
So what I'm understanding is that, you know, based on this משנה
Mishna and plenty of others, it all sounds like, you know, alright,
you know, like you just... you seem to just get the first
person that you find and maybe you don't know, right? We have
this other משנה Mishna that if you're me or I'm just and
I'm forgetting, maybe I've just gone, that like, you know, you got
no... you saw you'd need to check like eight...
Well, alright, the גמרא Gemara. is going to get to that a
little bit. Well, just because you're supposed to doesn't mean people did
and there's also, you know, different standards between ישראל and כהנים, right?
So some of the whole checking had to do
with כהנים going back even further.
No, that was when a כהן wanted to marry a בת ישראל,
bas Yisrael, he had to go back even further. Yes, Michael? The...
the last...
whatever your name is...
the last solution here, one gives a
גט get and the other marries her, I presume that's not going
to work if the guy is a כהן.
One minute...
the last solution here, one gives a גט get and the other
marries her. Right, I presume that's not going to work if the
guy is a כהן.
What do you mean? Oh, right, that's correct, correct, it will not
work for a כהן, yes, correct. Okay, so let's see the גמרא.
Gemara וצריכא, Utzricha, you need to tell me both the scenario of
the father making a שליח shaliach and of her making a שליח.
shaliach. דאי אשמעינן גבי דידיה, De'ee ashmi'inan gabei didey, if it had
just said by the father, משום דגברא קים ליה ביוחסין, mishum degavra
kom leh b'yuchsin, there you go Michael, the father knows, you know,
knows about who's מיוחס meyuchas to her and therefore he says, you
know what, I'm going to do it myself and I'll make sure
I get a nice מיוחס... meyuchas...
one minute, let me just check רש"י... Rashi... וחזא דמיוחסת קידשה לו.
v'chaza d'meyucheses kidsha lo. Okay, מיוחסת, meyucheses, one minute, מיוחס, meyuchas, okay.
כי שמצא מיוחסת כשלו, ki shematza meyucheses k'shelo,
וביטלה
לשליחותיה, u'veitlah lishlichusei,
right?
Right,
so the father says, "I know who I'll be able to find,
somebody who's מיוחס meyuchas for my daughter." So therefore when he went
and married off his and and did it himself, he was he
that took pre, you know, then then that negated the שליחות. shlichus.
He was really he was doing it for real. אבל, aval, so
what's that in contrast to? איתתא, itata, for the woman. Now, assuming
when the woman made a שליח shaliach she made a man as
a שליח, shaliach, okay? So she made a man as a שליח,
shaliach, so then "I'm sending a man to go to go find
for me a husband." So her presumption is that her male שליח
shaliach is more knows better than she does to find a guy
who's מיוחס. meyuchas. Okay, so therefore she to some degree really trusts
her male שליח shaliach more than she trusts herself. And therefore maybe
even if she were to do it herself, it was really like
"Only if my שליח shaliach doesn't find anyone." But if my שליח
shaliach finds somebody even after me, I'd rather the שליח's shaliach act
be binding than my own. That would have been the הוה אמינא.
hava amina.
Okay, ואיתתא דלא קים לה ביוחסין אימא לא הוו קידושי קידושין,
ve'itata delo kime
lei beyuchsin eima
lo havu kiddushei kiddushin,
maybe she doesn't want her קידושין kiddushin to be binding as long
as her male שליח shaliach finds somebody, she'll trust him more than
she'll trust herself. And what she did was only as a backup
if her שליח shaliach didn't find anyone. Okay, ואשמועינן גבי דידה, ve'ashmunan
gabi didah, now if we would only have taught it by her,
משום דאיתתא דייקא ומנסבא, mishum de'itata daika u'minsava,
because a woman actually pays attention to who she's marrying. Okay, אבל,
aval,
so therefore she marries this guy when she if she really wants
to and forget about her שליח. shaliach. אבל איהו, aval ihu, but
the father who's marrying off his daughter, אימא לא איכפת ליה, eima
lo ichpas leh, now that doesn't mean a man doesn't care who
he's marrying because the גמרא Gemara normally says a man more cares
who he's marrying than a woman cares who she's marrying. But a
father, what does he really care what husband he finds for his
daughter? Any guy will do as long as he'll take her in
and pay for her food. He doesn't really care so much, he's
not going to have to live with the guy, his daughter's going
to have to live with the guy. So in that case, since
he doesn't care so much, maybe he also is not really preferring
his guy over the שליח, shaliach, maybe he's just marrying somebody as
a backup if the שליח shaliach doesn't find anyone. But he's not
really wanting his act to take precedence over that of the שליח.
shaliach. Okay, so צריכא, tsricha, you need both cases. Fine.
It's not the הלכה, obviously, right? What? He's looking for his daughter,
she's looking for herself.
Right, that's the basic point, correct. Okay, איתמר, itmar, now, here's a
very interesting debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel which is going
to last us for the rest of the דף. daf. קידשה אביה
בדרך וקידשה עצמה בעיר. kidshah aviha baderech ve'kidshah atzma ba'ir. She went
ahead, her father went and he was off in the, you know,
he he was somewhere there in Connecticut and he married off his
daughter, and she was back in New in New York and she
married herself off. All right. וקידשה עצמה בעיר. ve'kidshah atzma ba'ir. והרי
היא בוגרת, ve'harei hi bogeres, and now we come to figure out
whose קידושין kiddushin took place and we look at her and we
see she's a בוגרת. bogeres.
She wasn't before?
הא, ha, but we don't know how old she was when they
were doing their acts of קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, if she was a
נערה na'ara when they did the קידושין, kiddushin, the father's act took
was binding and not her. If she was a בוגרת, bogeres, her
act was good, not the father's. Now we know she's a בוגרת,
bogeres, but
we don't know how old she was when they were doing their
respective acts of קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, so רב אמר הרי היא בוגרת
לפנינו, Rav amar harei hi bogeres lefaneinu, she's a בוגרת bogeres now,
we should assume she was a בוגרת bogeres when the acts of
קידושין kiddushin were taking place and right, which we're going to get
to, and the father's act was not binding and hers was. ושמואל
אמר, u'Shmuel amar, no, חיישינן לקידושי שניהם, chashinan le'kiddushei shneihem, now she's
a בוגרת bogeres but we know she started life as a קטנה
ktana and a נערה, na'ara, so we don't know which one to
weigh in favor of, her current status or her past status. So
therefore we have to say we don't know whose קידושין kiddushin was
binding, whether it was when she was a נערה na'ara or בוגרת,
bogeres, and it's like a case in the משנה, Mishna. both men
have to give her a גט. get. Okay, אימת, eimas, now the
גמרא Gemara says when did this these acts of קידושין kiddushin take
place? אילימא בתוך ששה, ileima betoch shisha, during the six months from
the time she became a נערה, na'ara, she had two pubic hairs,
within six months of that time, הא נמי רב הרי היא בוגרת
לפנינו, ha nami Rav harei hi bogeres lefaneinu, how would רב Rav.
then say, "Well now she's a בוגרת, bogeres, we'll assume she was
a בוגרת bogeres during that six months period," which was when she
right? So you understand life
basically, okay, here she's a נערה, na'ara, what, here she's a נערה,
na'ara, okay,
thank you, then there are six months,
okay, and now at this stage, what, draw her bigger, far bigger,
okay, and here she's a bigger, somewhat bigger. Here she's a בוגרת,
bogeres, now it could be though, we normally assume after six months
she automatically becomes a בוגרת. bogeres. But actually there's a discussion about
that she could actually have show certain signs of puberty about like
in terms of of growth of breast growth or whatever. that actually
make her a בוגרת bogeret that are actual physical signs of puberty,
okay? But we assume that that only happens after six months. We
assume that won't happen during six months, okay? So now here when
they're all, this is הרי היא בוגרת לפנינו, harei hi bogeret lefanenu,
right now, right, הרי היא בוגרת לפנינו. harei hi bogeret lefanenu. But
when did, we're looking at her now and we see that she's
a בוגרת. bogeret. But when were they doing their acts of קידושין,
kiddushin, okay? So they were doing their acts of קידושין kiddushin here,
okay? Here's this guy and he's saying הרי את, harei at, okay?
And then here's the guy with the father and he's saying הרי
בתך מקודשת לי, harei bitcha mekudeshet li, okay? All
right. They're doing their acts of קידושין kiddushin sometime during this period.
So we're saying that קשיא kashya she's a בוגרת bogeret now, but
why would we assume she would be a בוגרת bogeret when the
קידושין kiddushin took place during that six months? Presumably under most cases,
you know, she doesn't become a בוגרת bogeret during the first six
months, so we should assume that it she was a נערה, na'arah,
okay? אימא. eima. So the גמרא Gemara says אי נימא בתוך
שישה ובהני אמר רב הרי בוגרת לפנינו, i neima betoch shisha u'v'hanei
amar Rav harei bogeret lefanenu, who cares that she's a בוגרת bogeret
now? השתא דבגרה. hashta d'bagra. We would say we should say it
happened now, after six months, not during the six months, because we
should presume that that never that, you know, under normal circumstances that
never happens during the six months. אלא לאחר שישה. ela le'achar shisha.
Okay, let's say these acts happened after the six months, okay? Right?
So let's say here was where the six months were over, okay?
So if that's true and these acts happened here, so then why
would שמואל Shmuel disagree? After six months we're expecting her to become
a בוגרת, bogeret, okay?
אלא לאחר שישה ובהני אמר שמואל חוששין לקידושי שניהם. ela le'achar shisha
u'v'hanei amar Shmuel chosheshin l'kiddushei sheneihem. If the acts of קידושין kiddushin
took place after six months, why would we concern that she might
have been a נערה? na'arah? והאמר שמואל אין בין נערות לבגרות אלא
שישה חודשים בלבד. v'ha'amar Shmuel ein bein naarut l'bagrut ela shisha chodashim
bilvad. ושמואל v'Shmuel said there's it's once it's six months she's definitely
a בוגרת. bogeret. There's never more than six months. So what's the
case? Within six months we should presume it hasn't happened yet. Once
it's six months it definitely has happened. What's the debate?
A year later we
don't know when it was. So the גמרא Gemara says well you
could say that. The גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא דקדיש בההוא יומא
דמשלם שישה. lo tzricha d'kadish b'hahu yoma d'mashlim shisha. No, these acts
of קידושין kiddushin that the father and the daughter did happened on
the day of the six months. The day that you are expecting
her to actually achieve physical maturity. So by the end of the
day, שמואל Shmuel will say it definitely happened, but by the beginning
of the day, they're expecting it to happen sometime during that day,
but you don't know exactly when, okay? And the father married her
first and then she married herself. And you don't know when exactly
that happened. Did it happen at the beginning of the day? So
the father's קידושין kiddushin was no good. Or did it happen later
in the day and the father's קידושין kiddushin was good? Okay. בההוא
יומא דמשלם שישה. b'hahu yoma d'mashlim shisha. Okay. רב Rav אמר הרי
בוגרת לפנינו דהשתא בוגרת בצפרא נמי בוגרת. harei bogeret lefanenu dehashta bogeret
b'tzapra nami bogeret. Since now she's a בוגרת bogeret at 4 PM,
she was a בוגרת bogeret at 9 AM when the father did
the קידושין kiddushin and therefore the father's is no good. ושמואל אמר
Ve-Shmuel amar, השתא הוא דאתו סימנים. hashta hu d'atu simanim. No, we
assume it happened now. But since she started yesterday she was a
נערה, na'arah, we assume she continued to be a נערה na'arah until
we have evidence otherwise, even though now she's a בוגרת. bogeret. Okay.
So now what we are dealing with is the case where something
had a certain חזקה chazakah to begin with. It was a חזקה
chazakah that was in the process of changing. And now we have
evidence that it changed. What do we do with that uncertain time
between when we know it had that status old status and when
we know it has that new status? So as Michael correctly said,
this is the classic case of the מקווה. mikvah. Let's take a
look. שמואל Shmuel wouldn't say though the next day even if there
were no סימנים simanim she would still be a נערה? na'arah? No,
שמואל Shmuel would say once it's six months she's a בוגרת. bogeret.
מאי שנא ממקווה. mai shena mi'mikvah. Now how is this different from
a מקווה? mikvah? No, מקווה שנמדד ונמצא חסר. mikvah she'nimdad v'nimtza chaseir.
A מקווה mikvah was measured and you found it had less than
forty סאה. se'ah. Now you knew it started with forty סאה.
se'ah. Now you have thirty-nine. And this is a חזקה chazakah that's
in the process of changing because slowly a מקווה mikvah is losing
water.
Okay. So in that case, do you go by its past status
or its present status? Okay. So let's take a look. כל טהרות
שנעשו על גביו למפרע בין ברשות היחיד ובין ברשות הרבים טמאות. kol
teharot she'na'asu al gabav l'mafrea bein b'reshut ha'yachid u'vein b'reshut ha'rabim temeiot.
Everything that was done in the past, any dunkings that were done,
you assume everybody all objects and all people are טמא, tamei, even
if it took place in a רשות הרבים. reshut ha'rabim. רשות הרבים
reshut ha'rabim you normally say a ספק safek is טהור. tahor. But
this is saying we don't have a ספק. safek. Whether it's רשות
הרבים reshut ha'rabim or whether it's רשות היחיד reshut ha'yachid we say
it's וודאי vadai no good. So that seems like a total ruling
in favor of רב. Rav Right now it's חסר, chaseir, we assume
it was וודאי חסר vadai chaseir all the way back until we
knew definitely otherwise. Okay. So how does שמואל Shmuel how does what
does שמואל Shmuel say? According to שמואל Shmuel it should have been
a ספק. safek. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. שאני התם דאיכא
למימר העמד טמא על חזקתו. shani hatam d'ika l'meimar ha'amed tamei al
chazkato. but it's different. There the vessels or the people started as
טמא. tamei. So therefore they had a status quo as being טמא.
tamei. So a doubtful מקוה mikvah can't change their status. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, אדרבא, aderaba, העמד מקוה על חזקתו ואימר
לא חסר, he'med mikvah al chazkaso ve'eimar lo chaser, maybe I should
say the מקוה mikvah had a status of being full, and I
should say that it was full when it was used. גמרא Gemara
says no, הרי חסר לפניך. harei chaser lefanecha. That you know, that
status you know has changed because you see now that it's lacking.
So yes, you knew it was full but now you see it's
not full. So that you have the past status and the current
status and those are head-to-head. So what's going to therefore decide is
the person's חזקה chazaka of being טמא. tamei. Right? You get it?
The מקוה's mikvah two statuses sort of neutralize each other. Past you
knew it was good, present you know it's not good, those sort
of neutralize each other. I know that I was טמא, tamei, so
I don't know I went to a good מקוה, mikvah, so I
remain טמא. tamei. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי הרי
בוגרת לפניך. hacha nami harei bogeres lefanecha. Okay, but say the same
thing here, that you have the, she's now a בוגרת, bogeres, so
the same way we say there it's now a lacking מקוה, mikvah,
we should say now she's a בוגרת bogeres so she before was
a בוגרת. bogeres. גמרא Gemara says no, השתא דבגרה. hashtu d'bagra. No,
no, no, there we can say she just became a בוגרת bogeres
now. התם נמי השתא הוא דחסר. hasam nami hashtu hu d'chasar. Let's
say the מקוה mikvah just became חסר chasar right now. So גמרא
Gemara finally says, התם תרתי לריעותא הכא חדא לריעותא. hasam tarti l're'uso
hacha chada l're'uso. There there's two bad, here there's one bad. Which
means what? Which means, okay, you have basically
she started as a נערה, na'ara,
now she's a בוגרת. bogeres. Okay? Okay? And this,
so the current and this area in the middle, right, she's like
this area in the middle, that's the question in doubt. You don't
know which status to apply, the current status backwards or the past
status forwards. So this is all in doubt. Okay, that's why שמואל
Shmuel said it's לספק. l'safek. Don't go by now because you have
the past, don't go by the past because you have the now,
so the whole middle status is in ספק. safek. By the מקוה,
mikvah, it's the same thing, okay? You have the מקוה mikvah was
full, and then you have the מקוה mikvah that's חסר. chasar. So
that's in doubt. Okay? You're right, it's a ספק. safek. But in
this case, what trumps is that this guy, you know he was
טמא, tamei, okay, before he went into the מקוה. mikvah. So this
gets neutralized, so he remains טמא. tamei. So that's תרתי לריעותא. tarti
l're'uso. A, he's טמא, tamei, and B, right now it's חסר. chasar.
Okay? Which is a way of saying this neutralizes itself and therefore
you're going to trump based on this status quo. Here it neutralizes
itself, there's no status quo, so it remains a ספק. safek. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ובשמואל מאי שנא מחבית? u'b'Shmuel mai shna
me'chavit? Okay, so how is שמואל's Shmuel case different than the חבית?
chavit? דתניא, de'tanya, we learn in a ברייתא. braisa. היה בודק את
החבית להפריש עליה תרומה והולך. hayah bodek es hachavit l'hafrisha aleha terumah
v'holech.
So somebody had a חבית chavit filled with wine, and he's going
to anytime he needs to be מפריש תרומה mafrish terumah on some
wine that he's going to newly press, he's going to say yeah
two more ounces from that חבית chavit are תרומה, terumah, another two
ounces, another two ounces. And then once he has accounted for the
whole amount of wine in the חבית, chavit, he'll give it all
to a כהן. Okay. ואחר כך נמצא חומץ. v'acharka-kach nimtza chometz.
But then he goes and he checks that חבית chavit after a
few weeks and it's חומץ. chometz. So when was it, did it
become חומץ? chometz? Whenever it became חומץ, chometz, the תרומה terumah didn't
work. Okay, תרומה terumah only worked when it was
wine. כל ג' ימים ודאי מכאן ואילך ספק. kol gimmel yamim vadai
mi'kan v'eilach safek. The first three days it's ודאי, vadai, afterwards it's
a ספק. safek. Now first three days which way? There's a debate
in the גמרא Gemara, in another גמרא, Gemara. which is you can
read it that, okay it's the same idea, okay, here you have
as wine, and here you have as חומץ. chometz. Okay? And the
question is what's the story in the middle? Now there's two ways
of reading it. Some say the first three days, this is the
moment you checked it was wine, this moment you checked. The first
three days it's definitely חומץ. chometz. Here it's a ספק. safek. But
anything that was done in the last three days is definitely not
תרומה. terumah. Or the other read is the first three days after
checking the wine it's definitely wine, after and everything was good, afterwards
it's a ספק. safek. That's what I... Okay but the three days
doesn't really matter for us, for us what matters is, is that
it's a ספק. safek. Okay? But this should be like the מקוה
mikvah case because this is a ספק, safek, but your grain was
definitely טבל, tevel, right? So how's that going to work? Let's take
a look at the גמרא.
Gemara I wonder what it is any different?
Well let's take a look because it says it's a ספק. safek.
It doesn't say it's ודאי vadai not good. Okay? But let's take
a look. מאי שנא דהכא ודאי ומאי שנא דהכא ספק? mai shna
d'hacha vadai u'mai shna d'hacha safek?
Why by the case of מקוה mikvah do we say it was
ודאי טמא? vadai tamei? Because the very fact that we said that
this applies even in a רשות הרבים reshus harabim means we're saying
it's not a ספק, safek, it's ודאי טמא. vadai tamei. Why here
do we say it was ודאי טמא vadai tamei and here we
say it's ספק safek what the status is? ואמר רבי חנינא מסוריא
מאן תנא חבית רבי שמעון היא דגבי מקוה נמי ספיקא משוי ליה.
v'amar Rabbi Chanina mi'Surya man tanna chavis Rabbi Shimon hi d'gabbei mikvah
nami sefika mashavi lei. You know what?
You're right, it is no different. The one who says that this
case is a ספק safek is actually I was confusing it by
mentioning the status of the טבל, tevel, because the טבל tevel maybe
has a different status. Why do you say it was ודאי טמא
*vadai tamei* and here we say it's ספק safek. *safek* what the
status is? ואמר רב Rav חנינא מסוריא *V'amar Rav Chanina mi-Suria*, מאן
תנא חבית רבי שמעון היא *man tana chavi Rabi Shimon hi*, דגבי
מקוה נמי ספיקא משוי לה *d'gabei mikvah nami s'feika m'shavi leh*. You
know what? You're right, it is no different. The one who says
that this case is a ספק safek. *safek* is actually I was
confusing it by mentioning the status of the טבל *tevel*, because the
טבל *tevel* maybe has a different story, but in terms of this
stuff itself, right? Whether the טבל *tevel* is מתוקן *metukan* maybe that's
different. In terms of this wine itself, whether that's considered תרומה *terumah*,
okay, that should just be there's no חזקה chazaka. *chazakah*, you go
in both directions, and it should be ספק safek. *safek*. That makes
sense, okay. So how about, but that, but anyway, but how about
that's true, so why don't we say here too it's a ספק
safek *safek*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, מאי שנא הכא ודאי מאי
שנא הכא ספק safek *mai shna hacha vadai mai shna hacha safek*?
ואמר רב Rav חנינא מסוריא *V'amar Rav Chanina mi-Suria*, מאן תנא חבית
רבי שמעון היא *man tana chavi Rabi Shimon hi*. You know what?
You're right. The one who says that the חבית *chavis* is a
ספק *safek* is Rabbi Shimon, and Rabbi Shimon says דגבי מקוה נמי
ספיקא משוי לה *d'gabei mikvah nami safek mashvi leh*. And he says
the מקוה *mikvah* is also a ספק *safek*. What does he say
by מקוה *mikvah*? דתניא *De-tanya*: כל טהרה שנעשתה גביו למפרע בין ברשות
היחיד ובין ברשות הרבים טמאות *kol taharah she-na'asatah gavav l'mafrei'a bein b'reshut
hayachid u'vein b'reshut harabim t'mei'on*. He retroactively they're טמא *tamei*. That's what
we said; it's ודאי *vadai* no good. רבי שמעון אומר *Rabi Shimon
omer*: No. ברשות הרבים טהורות ברשות היחיד תלויות *B'reshut harabim tehorot, b'reshut
hayachid t'luyin*. In רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* they're definitely טהור *tahor*. In
רשות היחיד *reshut hayachid* they're a ספק *safek*. Okay, that he has
a general position that ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד *safek tumah b'reshut hayachid*
is ספק *safek*, not ודאי *vadai*. We don't have to worry about
that. Anyway, okay, so whatever it is, there's a way of reconciling
the חבית *chavis* with the מקוה *mikvah*. That the, that the חבית
*chavis* case is similar to the מקוה *mikvah* case. And if מקוה
*mikvah*, if חבית *chavis* is ספק *safek*, מקוה *mikvah* is ספק *safek*.
If מקוה *mikvah* is ודאי *vadai*, the חבית *chavis* is ודאי *vadai*.
But essentially it's the same case. So now we're going to say,
אבל לרבנן טבל למפרע *aval l'rabanan tevel l'mafrei'a*. Oh no. Okay, so
I was right the first time. Sorry. For the, it is a
חזקה chazaka *chazakah*. The same way here you have a חזקה chazaka
*chazakah* of the person being טמא *tamei*, here you have a חזקה
chazaka *chazakah* of your grain being טבל *tevel*. Okay. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, אי *ei*, so if you say here you go by
the ספק *safek*, then here you go by the ספק *safek*. That's
Rabbi Shimon. He says this is a ספק *safek* and this is
a ספק *safek*. But according to the רבנן rabbanan, *Rabanan*, this is
a ודאי *vadai*, you go by the חזקה chazaka. *chazakah* of him
being טמא *tamei*, and this is a ודאי *vadai*, you go by
the חזקה *chazakah* of it being טבל *tevel*. Okay. So fine, so
those are the same. How is it different than this case? And
the answer is once again going to be obvious. שאני התם *Shani
hasam*, because in this case you have תרתי Tarti *tarti*. You have
something that has a חזקה *chazakah*. In this case you don't have
anything that has a חזקה *chazakah*. Right, it's going to be the
same answer. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: שאני התם דאיכא
למימר העמד טבל על חזקתו *shani hasam de-ika l'meimar ha'amed tevel al
chazkato*. You have a חזקה *chazakah* of the טבל *tevel*. ואימא לא
נתקן *V'eima lo nisken*, it wasn't fixed. אדרבה העמד יין על חזקתו
ואימא לא החמיץ *Adaraba ha'amed yayin al chazkato v'eima lo hechmitz*. Say
the יין *yayin* has a חזקה *chazakah* of being wine. No, הרי
החמיץ לפנינו *harei hechmitz lifaneinu*. Now it's vinegar. הכא נמי הרי היא
בוגרת bogeres לפנינו *Hacha nami harei hi bogeres lifaneinu*. Here she's a
בוגרת bogeres *bogeres*. No, השתא דבגרה *Hashtu d'bagra*. We say it's a
בוגרת bogeres, *bogeres* now. השתא דהחמיץ *Hashtu d'hechmitz*. No, התם תרתי Tarti,
לריעותא הכא חדא לריעותא *hasam tarti l'rei'usa hacha chada l'rei'usa*. Same point.
Yes, in all these cases you have the current status and the
past status facing off. In all these cases you create a ספק
*safek*. The question is here, the man's חזקה *chazakah* being טמא *tamei*
is what dictates in a case of ספק *safek*. The wine's חזקה
*chazakah* being טבל *tevel* dictates in a case of ספק *safek*. Here
nothing dictates, so therefore it remains a ספק *safek* and it's ספק
קידושי מרה *safek kiddushei marra*. Right. Exactly.
Okay. נימא כתנאי
*Neima k'tana'ei*. Let's say this is fits, this is compared, links to
a debate of תנאים tana'im, *tanna'im*. מי מוציא מיד מי *Mi motzi
mi-yad mi*? Now, a guy is gives away all his property and
and then he is, if a person gives away all his property,
right? If a person gives away all his property on his deathbed,
and then he gets better, so the whole gift is, is void,
because we say he just gave it away expecting that he would
die. All right. Now, let's say a guy wrote gave away, wrote
away all his property, wrote it in a as a gift, as
a gift. Okay. And now he's walking around and he's healthy, and
he's saying, "Yeah, what I gave it away and I was on
my deathbed, now I'm doing better." And all the recipients of his
gift say, "You weren't on your deathbed when you gave it away,
you were fine and healthy when you gave it away." Okay. So
who gets to keep the property? So מי מוציא מיד מי *mi
motzi mi-yad mi*? Who can take it from whom? הוא מוציא מידם
בלא ראיה והם אינם מוציאין מידו בלא ראיה דברי רבי יעקב Rabbi
Ya'akov *Hu motzi mi-yadam b'lo ra'ayah v'hem einam motzi'in mi-yado b'lo ra'ayah,
divrei Rabi Ya'akov*. Rabbi Ya'akov says basically you believe him, which means
that you presume he did give it on his deathbed. Why? Presumably
because he was the original owner of the property. So therefore you
give him, they have the burden of proof. Okay. רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan אומר *Rabi Nasan omer*: No. ברי הוא עליו להביא ראיה *Barri
hu alav l'havi ra'ayah*. If now he's healthy, he has to prove
that he was on his deathbed when he gave it away. You,
you look at his current status. And that makes us presume what
it was when he gave away the
property. Okay. שכיב מרע *she-shchiv mera*. If if if now he's on
his deathbed, then עליהם להביא ראיה שברי היה *aleihem l'havi ra'ayah she-barri
hayah*. They have to bring a proof that he was healthy. So
נימא רב Rav דאמר כרבי נתן *neima Rav d'amar k'Rabi Nasan*? Let's
say Rav goes like Rabbi Nasan, because Rav says you look at
his current status and you assume his current status was what was
true before, the same way Rav says now she's a בוגרת bogeres,
*bogeres* she was a בוגרת bogeres. *bogeres* before. ושמואל v'Shmuel דאמר כרבי
יעקב *U'Shmuel d'amar k'Rabi Ya'akov*? And Shmuel says, "No, you know, you
don't look at his current status," and you go by and therefore
you would just go by what the normal state of the property
was, which was in his possession. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, "No."
אמר לך רב Rav *Amar lach Rav*, Rav could say to you,
"אנא דאמרי אפילו כרבי יעקב *ana d'amri afilu k'Rabi Ya'akov*. I could
go even like Rabbi Ya'akov, who says that you don't go by
his current status of being healthy." property away from him. עד כאן
לא קאמר רבי יעקב התם,
why does רבי יעקב say you ignore his current status? דאיכא למימר
הוי ממונא בחזקתו, de-ika le-meimar havei mamona be-chezkato,
same point before about you have neutralizing but you have some other
חזקה. So yes, here, maybe right now he's healthy, but you have
some other thing that factors in, which is the property had a
חזקה in being under his ownership. אבל הכא מי נימא אמת גופא
חזקתו? Aval hacha mi neima hemet gufa chezkato?
But here, the body did not have a חזקה of not changing,
it was actually in the process of changing. Okay, so yes, by
the case of בוגרת bogeres, I'll say she was a בוגרת bogeres.
this morning because the body was in the process of changing. But
in this case, I'm going to say I don't know whether he
was sick or not when he gave away the property, but what
I do know is the property was under his possession and I'll
assume it remains under his possession.
So תרתי again, just
so, yeah, not exactly similar to the תרתי, yeah. אבל הכא מי
נימא אמת גופא חזקתו? Aval hacha mi neima hemet gufa chezkato? ושמואל
אמר, שמואל Shmuel would say, אנא דאמרי אפילו כרבי נתן. ana de-amri
afilu ke-Rabbi Natan. I could say even like רבי נתן who says
that you go by the current status. And if currently he's healthy,
you assume he was healthy before and you would actually give the
property away to the recipient, right? Why would we take the property
out of his חזקה if you know, עד כאן לא קאמר רבי
נתן התם Ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Natan hatam דכולי עלמא בחזקת
בריאים קיימי, de-chulei alma be-chezkat bri'im kaimei, because most people are not
on their deathbed. You want to make a claim you're on your
deathbed, what's your evidence? Okay, it's very different in this case. We
know she started as a נערה, na'ara, we know she's now a
בוגרת, bogeres, we know she was in the process of changing, that
creates a whole ספק. There, who the heck why should we assume
you were on your deathbed? I know, but there's no evidence you
were on your deathbed and the fact and the fact that you're
healthy now, combined with the reality that most people aren't on their
deathbed, is strong enough to take the property out of your possession.
Okay, מאן דקא נפיק נפשיה מחזקה, man de-ka nafik nafshia mi-chazaka, if
you want us to take you out of the presumption that you
were healthy, הוי עליה ראיה, havei alei ra'aya,
you'd have to prove it. אבל הכא מי כאן מפקת נפשיה מחזקה
דקמיה? Aval hacha mi kan mafkit nafshia mi-chazaka de-kamei? Here she's not
taking herself out of some חזקה. Okay, she started as a נערה,
na'ara, now she's a בוגרת, bogeres? both of those are
reasonable statuses that she could have and the question is just when
she had it. So therefore that remains a ספק. All right, last
attempt. We're going to get to the משנה today.
נימא כהני תנאי? Neima ke-hanei tana'ei? Maybe it's like these תנאים, which
actually seems like there's an explicit מחלוקת תנאים machlokes tana'im which is
exactly רב Rav, and שמואל. Shmuel. קדשה אביה בדרך וקדשה עצמה בעיר.
Kidshiya aviha ba-derech ve-kidshiya atzma ba-ir. Her father married her on the
way and she married herself in the city, והרי בוגרת לפנינו. ve-harei
bogeres lefaneinu. And now she's a בוגרת. bogeres תנא חד הרי היא
בוגרת לפנינו, Tana chad harei hi bogeres lefaneinu, you go by her
current status, you assume her father's קידושין kiddushin was not binding, it
was her קידושין. kiddushin. Now she's a בוגרת, bogeres then she was
a בוגרת. bogeres ותניא אידך, Ve-tanya idach, the other ברייתא baraita says,
no, חיישינן לקידושי שניהם, chaishinan le-kiddushei sheneihem, you don't know when she
became a בוגרת, bogeres and she's married potentially to either man, she
needs a גט get from both men. מאי לאו חד כרב וחד
כשמואל? Mai lav chad ke-Rav ve-chad ke-Shmuel? That sounds like the debate
of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, that exactly corresponds to the debate.
No, לא אידי ואידי כשמואל. lo idi ve-idi ke-Shmuel. I could say
they're both going like
שמואל. Shmuel. כאן במכחשת כאן בשאין מכחשת. Kan be-machacheshat kan be-she-ein machacheshat.
What is she saying? What is she saying about when she became
a בוגרת? bogeres So maybe we go like שמואל Shmuel that says
that it's a ספק. But we will go like רב and say
that we trust that she was a בוגרת bogeres earlier when she
actually claims she was a בוגרת earlier. If we don't know, she
says I don't know when this happened, then it's a ספק like
שמואל. Shmuel. But maybe שמואל Shmuel himself would agree to רב when
she says she became a בוגרת earlier in the day
and that's the only point.
Like our משנה about the, something like our משנה. ונימא מדי מתניתא
לא פליגי, Ve-neima mi-de-matnisa lo pligi, that's how you're going to reconcile
the ברייתות. baraitas. אמוראי נמי לא פליגי, Amora'ei nami lo pligi, maybe
רב and שמואל Shmuel aren't in disagreement. Maybe רב is talking about
a case when she makes a claim and שמואל Shmuel is talking
about a case when she doesn't make a claim. The גמרא says,
תסבורא, tisbira, does that really make sense that they are not disagreeing?
הא רב יוסף בריה דרב מנשיא מדביל עבד עובדא כותיה דרב, Ha
Rav Yosef breia de-Rav Menashya mi-Devill avad uvda kevata de-Rav, he ruled
like רב, that said she was a בוגרת and rejected the father's
קידושין kiddushin and went by her קידושין. kiddushin. ואיקפד שמואל Ve-ikpad Shmuel
and שמואל Shmuel got very upset. How could you be so lenient
and say, oh, we definitely know that it was her קידושין kiddushin
and not the father's, she was a בוגרת in the morning? Right?
That's taking, that's playing with fire, maybe it's the father's קידושין kiddushin
was binding. ואמר כולי עלמא כיילי ליה בקבא זוטא, Ve-amar kulei alma
kailei leih be-kava zuta,
everybody else just uses a small basket, like, given their wisdom in
a small basket. והאי מדרבנן כיילי ליה בקבא רבה? Ve-hai mi-derabbanan kailei
leih be-kava raba? You were giving this רבנן, rabbanan, this no-name רבנן,
all of a sudden he got his wisdom in a big basket?
Like, he's so smart, you're such a big חכם, chacham, you know
more than anybody else. Normal big רבנים Rabbanim would think it's a
ספק and would be trepidatious to פסקן about this case. And you
all of a sudden are such a big חכם chacham that you
know that we can go like רב and you know that the
father, that she was a בוגרת in the morning and you don't
have to worry about the קידושין kiddushin of the father.
Encouraging him pedagogically. Exactly.
Okay, he is,
he's indeed teaching him a lesson. So anyway, you see רב *Rav*
and שמואל *Shmuel* actually disagree, right? Because he's actually, if רב *Rav*,
if they weren't disagreeing, then why would he be upset he פסקן
*paskens* like רב *Rav* if he also agrees with רב *Rav* if
she makes a claim? So גמרא *Gemara* says no, דילמא כי עביד
עובדא במכחשתיה *dilma ki avid uvda b'machashto*, and if they really, if
they really didn't disagree, why is שמואל *Shmuel* getting so upset? Maybe
that was a case where she where she made a claim. So
it sounds like רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* really are disagreeing. Okay.
אמר ליה מר זוטרא לרב אשי הכי אמר מימר הלכתא כוותיה דשמואל
*Amar lei Mar Zutra l'Rav Ashi, hachi amar Meimar, hilchata k'vatei d'Shmuel*,
we rule like שמואל *Shmuel*, ורב אשי אמר הלכתא כוותיה דרב *v'Rav
Ashi amar hilchata k'vatei d'Rav*, we rule like רב *Rav*, והלכתא כוותיה
דרב *v'hilchata k'vatei d'Rav*, we rule like רב *Rav*. Oh, the גמרא
*Gemara* is a little bit unclear at the end. Does that mean
even if they're not contradicting or only when they're contradicting? It sounds
like, but there's questions of the גרסא *girsa*, questions exactly how to
read that last piece we did. The way we read it, it
sounds like we would rule she's ודאי בוגרת *vadai bogeret*, you don't
go by the father's קידושין *kiddushin*, even even if she doesn't contradict
him. But it is possible that obviously we're talking in a case
where she does contradict him and that would be more reason to
say that you believe her and you believe that she was a
בוגרת *bogeret* in the morning.
Okay.